#### Joanes Ooko Odero

Cell: +254715600900, +254736413102 | Email: joanesooko@gmail.com

### **Career Summary**

Dynamic, goal-oriented environmentalist and sustainable development enthusiast with vast experience in advocacy, capacity building and design of climate change-smart and climate resilient best practices. I possess demonstrable knowledge of national and international climate change response strategies and policies, strategic environmental and social assessments, and environmental advisory. I am goal-driven professional who strives to exceed expectations daily.

### Education

September 2017- in progress - Kenyatta University, Nairobi Kenya

Master of Science in Integrated Watershed

Management (Research project)

September 2010 – December 2014 - Kenyatta University

Bachelor of Environmental Studies (Community Development)

### Experience

January 2019 to date.

**Environment Specialist at EcoSafe Holdings** 

- Work with the project manager to organize project meetings that involve progress reviews and future planning to ensure all team members are on the same page.
- Facilitate community participation and capacity building programs on livelihood improvement through Focus Group Discussions (FGDs).
- Liaise with the National Environmental Managing Authority on project licensing and compliance with municipalities and national legislation.
- Manage scheduling and deadlines of projects to ensure progress is on target and that deadlines are still feasible.
- Monitor and identify potential issues or risks that may hinder project progress, and take the effective steps to ensure risks are limited and reduced.
- Establish partnerships and represent the organization in meetings with various organizations in the industry.
- Review and assist in developing operational monitoring tools like questionnaires, interview guides, and checklists.
- Prepare environmental impact assessment and climate change consultancy services and EIA technical proposals.

### March 2014 Environment and Climate Change Specialist at Dayton Consultants to Dec. 2018

- Conducted Environmental and Social Impact Assessment (ESIA), and Environmental Audits in accordance with the Environmental Management and Coordination Act (EMCA), 1999, IFC Standards, Equator Principles, and World Bank Guidelines.
- Reviewed and contributed to the mainstreaming climate change and green growth into value-chain, infrastructure projects, and company policy frameworks.
- Supported the proponents in identifying, preparing and implementing project components to address climate change issues and climate change readiness.

• Developed comprehensive Environmental and Social Management Plan to ensure best environmental practices during the entire project cycle.

## **Apr. – Sep. 2013** Intern at Lake Victoria Environment Management Project Phase II (KISUMU)

- Assisted Environment Specialist to commission research and publish reports on climate change adaptation tools, methods, and frameworks.
- Helped the Climate Change Adaptation Adviser to incorporate the local views and positions on adaptation issues during formulation of Kenya National Adaptation Plan 2015-2030.
- Assisted in planning and implementation of the Community Driven Development subprojects with regards to enhancing climate change resilience and adaptation in Kisumu, Homa Bay and Migori

# Apr. - Sep 2012 Volunteer at UMANDE TRUST –Sustainable Environment and Community Development (SECODE) (KISUMU)

- Initiated development projects aimed at uplifting the living standards of Orphans and vulnerable children like urban agriculture, poultry farming, and waste management.
- Supported the development of funding opportunities for UMANDE TRUST's work on community development
- Contributed to the organization's internal reporting, supporter inquiries, communications and fundraising activities
- Assisted the editorial team of the community newspaper to publish comprehensive articles regarding environmental and social concerns and opportunities in the informal settlements of Kisumu.

### **Other Assignments**

- June 2014 University College of London (Field Study Guide-Kisumu)
  - Field Research on Youth Empowerment and HIV/AIDs
    - ✓ Successfully planned and facilitated community meetings and data collection forums (Focus Group Discussions, Key Informant Interviews).
    - ✓ Acted as an intermediary between the students and the community/study participants by doing interpretations to aid communication.
- April 2015 Successfully coordinated a workshop on Delegated Management Model (DMM) organized by Kisumu Urban Apostolate Programmes (Pandipieri) for Manyatta and Obunga Slums Residents

#### **Outcomes of the workshop**

- ✓ Enhanced local people's knowledge of water management and conservation
- ✓ Improved understanding of DMM and water operation issues
- ✓ Improved knowledge of issues including non-revenue water, billing, illegal connection, disconnection, and reconnection

### **Skills & Ability**

Good knowledge of Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint) GIS and Remote Sensing, SPSS

Professional Affiliation
Member of Environment Institute of Kenya (EIK).

Certified Environmental Impact Assessment Expert by the National Environmental Management Authority (NEMA)

### Referees

Stanley Ambasa	Naftal Ratemo	Professor Joy Obando
Senior NEMA Environment Officer,	Director - Ecosafe Holdings Ltd.	Senior Lecturer Kenyatta University
Phone No. 0716297939	Phone No. 0726223400	Phone No. 0722966134
Email: ambasas2000@yahoo.co.uk	Email: ecosafeholdings@gmail.com	Email: obando.joy@ku.ac.ke